Lost Bonds
（ナルト）俺たち
第七班でやってきたことは→
Don't all those things we did
together in Squad 7
全部　何の意味もなかったのかよ？
mean anything to you?!
（サスケ）いや　無意味じゃない。
No… It wasn't meaningless.
俺にとってお前は　最も→
To me, you became…
親しい友になった。
my closest friend.
友になった？　だったら何で？
I became your friend?
Then why?
だからこそだ。
That's precisely why.
だからこそ→
That's precisely why…
お前には殺す価値がある。
you're worth killing.
（ヤマト）気がついたか？
You're finally awake?
夢…。
A dream?
俺ってば…。
Where am I?
気絶したんだよ。
You lost consciousness.
心配かけてホント…。
You really had us worried.
カカシ先生とサイは？
Where are Kakashi Sensei and Sai?
そうか。
I see.
何でだ？
Why?
何で　こうなっちまう？
Why did it turn out like this?
ナルト　もう少し休んだほうがいい。
Naruto…
You should rest a bit longer.
さあ。
Come on.
《サスケ　お前は…》
Sasuke…you're…
((知ってるか？
Did you hear?
Everyone in the Uchiha Clan got killed.
うちは一族って
みんな殺されたらしいぜ。
ああ　知ってる知ってる。
父ちゃんが言ってた。
Yeah, I know.
I heard my dad talking about it.
(生き残ったの　アイツだけらしいぜ))
He's the only one who survived.
《あのとき俺は　嬉しかった。
I was sorta glad back then.
同じ孤独なヤツがいることが…》
I wasn't the only one
who was alone anymore.
《だけどサスケは
何をやっても　うまくできた》
But Sasuke was good
at everything he did.
((イルカ：おお　やるなサスケ。
Good job, Sasuke!
（イノ）さすがサスケ君！
（サクラ）かっこいい！
Just what I'd expect from Sasuke!
He's so cool!
ヘッ　かっこつけやがって。
He's showing off!
I can do that too!
(あんなの
俺にだって　できるってばよ))
《俺とは違ってた》
He was so different from me.
((行け！))
Go!
《だから勝手に　ライバルに決めた。
That's why I picked him
to be my rival,
アイツみたいになりたかったから》
because I wanted to
become like him.
((でや～！))
《同じ七班になっても→
Even though we were both on Squad 7,
サスケは　俺より一歩前にいた》
Sasuke was always
one step ahead of me.
《必死に修業したのは→
The reason why I trained so hard
was because
少しでも
追いつきたかったからだった》
I wanted to catch up to him,
even just a little.
俺は強いのか？
"Am I strong?"
All I want is the answer to that.
ただその答えがほしい。
ここで　強いヤツと
戦いたかっただけだ。
I just wanted to fight the strong ones.
そして　ソイツらは　ここにいる。
And they are all right here.
(ナルト　俺はお前とも戦いたい))
Naruto… I want to fight you too.
《本当に嬉しかった。
I was really happy.
サスケが　俺を認めてくれた
初めての言葉》
It was the first time Sasuke
acknowledged me as an equal.
((カカシ：そうだな　まずは
自己紹介してもらおう))
First off, let's have you guys
introduce yourselves.
《だけど　アイツは…》
But he…
名は　うちはサスケ。
My name's Sasuke Uchiha.
嫌いなものなら　たくさんあるが
好きなものは別にない。
I have lots of dislikes,
but no likes in particular.
それから　夢なんて言葉で
終わらす気はないが→
And I don't feel like summing up
my ambition as just a dream,
野望はある。
but I do have an ambition.
一族の復興と
ある男を必ず殺すことだ。
The ambition to restore my clan and
to kill a certain man
without fail!
（イタチ）久しぶりだな　サスケ。
It's been a long time…Sasuke.
うちはイタチ。
えっ！？
Itachi Uchiha…
アンタを殺す！
I will kill you!
《コイツが　サスケが言っていた
殺したい男》
This is the guy
Sasuke talked about,
the man he wants to kill?
アンタの言ったとおり
アンタを恨み　憎み→
It's just as you said…
I've hated you…
and resented you.
そして　アンタを殺すためだけに
俺は…。
For the singular purpose
of killing you, I…
俺は…。
I…
(生きてきた！))
have lived my life!
《お前は
復讐に生きることを決めた》
You decided to live for revenge.
((サイ：確かに　僕の極秘任務の命は
サスケ君の暗殺だった。
My classified mission was indeed
the assassination of Sasuke.
けど　命令はもういい。
But I've had enough of orders.
今は自分の考えで動きたい。
I now want to act
on my own beliefs.
ナルト君が
思い出させてくれそうなんだ。
I think Naruto will get me
to remember…
僕の昔の気持を。
my past emotions.
僕は　キミのことを
よく知らないけど→
I don't know you very well.
ナルト君やサクラさんが
ここまで必死に　キミを追うのには→
But there must be
some kind of reason
Naruto and Sakura have pursued
you so desperately.
何か　わけがある。
キミとのつながりを切るまいと→
They don't want to sever
their bonds with you.
つなぎとめておこうと
必死になってる。
They're giving it their all
to secure those bonds.
僕には　まだ
はっきりとは　わからない。
I still don't understand it
all that clearly.
けど　サスケ君
キミには　わかってるはずだ。
But Sasuke, you should understand.
ああ　わかってた。
Yeah, I did understand.
だから　断ち切った。
That's why I severed the bonds.
I have a different bond.
俺には　別のつながりがある。
(兄との憎しみっていう
つながりがな))
A bond of hatred with
my older brother.
《俺とサスケのつながりは…》
What about the bond
between Sasuke and me?
((さっさとこい！
その前に　額あてしろ。
Hurry up!
Before that, put your headband on.
I'll wait.
待ってやる。
いらねえよ　そんなもんは。
I don't need that thing.
いいから　しろ！
お前は　俺の額に→
Just do it!
You won't even be able to put
a scratch on my forehead!
傷一つ　つけることすら
できやしない。
That's not it!
違う　これは木ノ葉の忍として→
I'm saying this is a testament
対等に戦う証だって
言ってんだよ。
to fighting on equal terms
as Leaf Ninja.
そういうのが
図にのってるっていうんだ！
And I'm saying you're acting
high and mighty!
テメエと俺が
対等だと思ってんのか？
Do you really think that we're equals?!
ああ　思ってる。
俺は　一度も→
Yeah, I do!
I've never once thought that
I was inferior to you!
お前に劣ってるとは
思ったことはねえよ。
目障りなんだよ！
それは　お前が→
You're an embarrassment!
That's because you're still weak,
Little Sasuke!
弱いままだからだろうが。
サスケちゃんよ。
ナルト！
サスケ！
Naruto!
Sasuke!
Stop it, both of you.
やめて　２人とも。
Stop it!
やめてよ！
２人とも　やめて！
Stop it, both of you!
クソ！
止め切れねえ。
Damn!
I can't stop completely!
うわぁ！
Lord Orochimaru has already
acquired the Immortality Jutsu.
（君麻呂）大蛇丸様は
すでに不死の術を手にしている。
不死といっても　肉体がそのまま
保ち続けるわけではない。
"Immortal" doesn't mean that
his flesh can maintain itself forever.
体が朽ちる前に
強く新しい肉体を→
Before his body decays,
a strong, new body must be made
into a vessel for his soul.
魂の器にする。
それが…　それが
サスケだってのか！？
That's…
Are you saying that's Sasuke?!
ああ　そうだ。
Yes… That's right.
そんなこと　俺がさせるか！？
I won't let that happen!
《サスケが里を捨てたとき→
When Sasuke abandoned the village,
俺は　アイツを連れ戻せると
思っていた。　だけど…》
I really believed
I could bring him back.
But…
((いい加減に目が覚めたかよ！
Have you snapped out of it yet?
親も兄弟もいねえ　テメエに
俺の何がわかるってんだよ！
You have no siblings or parents.
How could you understand
anything about me?!
初めから１人きりだった　テメエに
俺の何がわかるってんだ！
You've been on your own
since the beginning!
What makes you think
you know anything about me?
つながりがあるからこそ
苦しいんだ。
Having that bond is
what makes it painful!
それを失うことが　どんなもんか→
And how could you know
(お前なんかに
わかってたまるか！))
what it feels like
to lose that bond?!
《結局　俺は　サスケのことを
何もわかっちゃいなかった。
In the end,
I didn't understand Sasuke at all.
わかったつもりで
いただけだった》
I just thought I knew him.
((何でだ？
何で　そこまでして俺に。
Why?
Why would you go
so far for me?
俺にとっちゃ
やっとできた　つながりなんだ。
Because this is the first bond
that I've ever had!
だから俺は
お前を止めるんだってばよ！
That's why I'm gonna stop you.
認めてやるよ　お前は強い。
I admit it, you're strong.
なぜなら　お前も俺と同じ
孤独の痛みを知る者だ。
It's because you know the pain
that solitude brings,
just as I do.
そして　その痛みが人を強くする。
And it's that pain that
makes people stronger.
だからこそ
このつながりを断つことで→
And for that very reason,
if I break that bond,
俺は　更なる強さを手に入れる。
I'll be able to achieve
even greater strength.
知ってるか？　ここは
終末の谷と呼ばれる国境だ。
Did you know that this place
is called the Final Valley?
ちょうどいい舞台じゃねえか
なあ　ナルト。
Don't you think this is
a perfect stage for us, Naruto?
You…
(じゃあ　そろそろしまいにしようぜ
この戦いを))
So let's bring this fight
to a close soon!
気分はどう？
おかゆを作ってもらったよ。
How are you feeling?
I had them make some porridge.
これを食べて
体力を回復するんだ。
Eat it and restore your strength.
今　サスケの夢を見てた。
I…was dreaming about Sasuke.
お前は　僕と一緒に里へ帰る。
You're going back to
the village with me.
カカシ先輩の命令だよ。
They're Kakashi's orders.
悪いけど　サスケのことは
カカシ先輩に任せるんだ。　いいね？
I'm sorry, but you just have to
let Kakashi handle Sasuke.
Got it?
わかってる。
Fine.
Let me rest some more,
then we can head back to the village.
もう少し休んだら
里に戻るってばよ。
体調を戻すためにも
少しは食べたほうがいい。
You should eat a little
to restore your strength.
食欲なんて　ねえってばよ。
I don't have an appetite.
((サスケは　俺とのつながりを
断ち切って→
Sasuke said he was going to sever
his bond with me
and become stronger.
強くなるって言ってた。
He said I could never
understand his feelings.
お前なんかに
俺の気持はわからないって。
エロ仙人と　大蛇丸も
昔　友達だったんだろ？
You were friends with Orochimaru
long ago, right, Pervy Sage?
どうして　大蛇丸は里を抜けて→
Why did Orochimaru desert the village
木ノ葉くずしなんか
したんだってばよ？
and decide to destroy
the Hidden Leaf?
（自来也）大蛇丸が
おかしくなってきたのは→
Orochimaru changed after
his parents were killed.
両親を殺されてからだ。
それからは
禁術にとりつかれていった。
He became obsessed
with Forbidden Jutsu.
両親に会いたかったのか。
Maybe he longed to see his parents,
それとも　両親を死に追いやった
木ノ葉への復讐か。
or he sought revenge
on the Leaf Village,
who he held responsible
for their deaths.
わしは　親を殺されては
おらんからのう。
My parents weren't killed.
わしも　お前と同じだ。
So like you, I was accused of
not being able to understand.
アイツに何もわかってないと
一喝されてのう。
そのとおり　アイツのことを→
Perhaps he was right,
I didn't understand
a thing about him.
何も　わかって
やれんかったのかもしれん。
だがのう　こんなわしでも
この忍の世に→
However…
even I can see there's too much
hate in our Ninja World.
憎しみが
はびこっているのはわかる。
憎しみ？
Hate?
その憎しみをどうにかしたいとは
思っとるんだが。
And I've wanted to do
something about this hatred,
どうしたらいいのか
わしにも　まだわからん。
but I'm not sure what
must be done.
だが　いつかは。
But I have faith that
there will come a time
人が本当の意味で
理解しあえる時代が来ると→
when people can truly
understand one another.
(わしは信じとる))
To me, Pervy Sage was irreplaceable.
He was family.
《俺にとって　エロ仙人は
かけがえのない家族だった》
《だから…》
That's why…
((フカサク：自来也ちゃんが戦死した。
Jiraiya-boy has died in battle.
(はあ？))
《エロ仙人が死んだって
聞いたとき→
When I heard that Pervy Sage died,
サスケの言っていた→
I understood what Sasuke was
talking about for the very first time.
絆を失うことの
つらさってやつが→
About the pain of losing a bond.
初めてわかった》
ナルト　そろそろ行くよ。
Naruto, let's go soon.
Are you still not ready?
まだか？
今は　外に出る気にならねぇんだ。
I don't feel like going outside yet.
もうちょっと待ってよ。
Can you wait a bit longer?
《よし！　まだ俺が影分身だって
気づかれてねえってばよ》
All right. He still hasn't caught on
that I'm a Shadow Clone.
((少しは　痛みを理解できたか？
Have you come to understand
a little of what pain is?
同じ痛みを知らなければ
他人を本当には理解できない。
Unless you know the same pain,
you cannot truly know another.
And even if you get to know others,
there can be no understanding.
そして　理解をしたところで
わかりあえるわけでもない。
それが　道理だ。
That is the truth.
お前が　サスケを追いかけても
ムダなようにな。
Just like how it's useless
to chase after Sasuke.
（カブト）人は変わる。
People change…
Sasuke isn't the old Sasuke anymore.
サスケ君は
もう昔のサスケ君じゃないんだよ。
（マダラ）サスケ自身が
そう選択したのさ。
Sasuke chose this himself.
サスケのことは　あきらめるんだのう。
You must forget about Sasuke.
忍として生きるなら
もっと賢くなれ。
If you are a ninja, become wiser.
バカのままじゃ　この世界
生きづらいのが現実だ。
Fools cannot survive in our world.
That is the reality.
賢いってのが
そういうことなら→
If being smart means
what you say,
I'll remain a fool for
the rest of my life.
(俺は　一生　バカでいい！))
Pervy Sage, I'm a big fool after all.
《エロ仙人…　やっぱ俺は
大バカだってばよ！》
カカシ先生のチャクラ！
Kakashi Sensei's chakra…
こっちか！
This way!
Sakura, don't do anything reckless.
《サクラちゃん！　ムチャすんなよ！》
((サイ：ここからは
僕の想像ですが→
This is just an assumption
on my part.
恐らく　サクラは…。
But I believe Sakura…
She intends to kill Sasuke herself.
(１人で　サスケを殺すつもりだな))
((サスケは　うちはの憎しみを
すべて背負い→
Sasuke has shouldered
the entire burden of the Uchiha's hatred
その憎しみの呪いを
世界へぶつけるつもりだ。
and intends to strike
the world with that curse.
最も強い武器であり
友であり力である憎しみ。
It is the most powerful weapon.
It's his friend and source of power,
this thing called hatred.
And it is Sasuke's Ninja Way!
(それがサスケの忍道だ))
((知ってるか？　ナルト。
Did you know, Naruto?
一流の忍同士なら
拳を一度交えただけで→
When two shinobi are of
a high enough level,
they are able to read
each other's thoughts,
simply by an exchange of fists.
互いの心の内が読めちまう。
口には出さなくてもだ。
Without ever uttering
a single word.
お前は甘いな　ナルト。
You're naïve, Naruto.
どうだ　お前には
本当の心の内が読めたか？
Tell me, could you read…
(この俺の))
my true feelings?
《サスケ　今なら→
Sasuke… Right now…
I understand how you feel as
someone who has lost a bond.
絆を失った　お前の気持
わかるってばよ》
((イタチ：さっき　お前は
サスケを兄弟のようだと言ったな。
You said earlier you consider
Sasuke to be like a brother.
What if Sasuke were to attack
the Leaf Village?
ならば　もし　そのサスケが
木ノ葉を襲ってきたら→
What would you do then?
どうすると聞いているんだ。
What? Why would Sasuke…?
何だ？　なんでサスケが…
そんなことするわけねえだろ！
There's no way he'd do
something like that!
サスケは　まだ純粋だ。
Sasuke is still naïve.
He can easily be dyed any color.
簡単に何色にでも染まる。
Would you be able to stop him?
そうなった場合
お前はヤツを止められるのか？
サスケを殺してでも。
Even if you had to kill Sasuke?
サスケと木ノ葉を
天秤にかけられるのか？
Could you weigh Sasuke
against the Leaf Village
on a set of scales?
木ノ葉は守る！
I would defend the Leaf Village!
そんでもってサスケも
殺さず止める！
But I would also stop Sasuke
without killing him!
子供だな。
お前の話は絵空事ばかりだ。
You're such a child.
What you speak of are
all fantasies.
A ninja must sometimes
make very harsh decisions.
(忍は時に厳しい選択を
迫られることだってある))
((雷影：暁は国際指名手配となる。
The Akatsuki will be branded
as wanted fugitives.
Then, not only I,
そうなれば　わしだけではない。
世界がサスケを狙う。
but the whole world will
hunt Sasuke down.
犯罪者のために頭を下げ
仲間の安全のために慈悲を請う。
Yet you bow your head
for this criminal
and plead for mercy for your friend.
In the ninja world,
that is not friendship!
(忍の世界で
それは友情とは言わん))
((我愛羅：影の名を
背負う覚悟を決めたなら→
If you are prepared to bear
the burden of being a Kage,
(サスケの友として　お前が本当に
やるべきことをやれ))
then d
《何をすべきかなんて
俺にもわからねえ。　だけど…》
((木ノ葉のガキ　お前が何をすべきか
もっと考えろ。
(バカのまま　やり通せるほど
忍の世界は甘くない！))
((俺は　お前を友だと思っている。
かつての俺にとって
友とは　ただの言葉。
それ以上でも
それ以下でもなかった。
だがお前と会って気づかされた。
大切なのは　その言葉の意味だと。
その意味するところが何なのか。
お前はサスケのために
何をしてやれるのか。
(よく考えろ))
《サスケ　お前に会えば…。
会えば　答えがわかる気がする》
（くもじい）
もしもし　そこのあなた。
たまには　空から日本を
眺めてみるというのは→
どうじゃろう？
今回は　瀬戸内海の島々を繋ぐ
しまなみ海道じゃ。
（くもみ）うわぁ　大きな橋。
海の交差点
瀬戸内海の船たちを眺めながら→
魅惑の島々を探検じゃ。
島がたくさん！